I would like to tell you a story
أريد أن أخبركم بقصة تربط ما بين
connecting the notorious privacy incident
الحادثة الشهيرة المتعلقة بالخصوصية
involving Adam and Eve,
لآدم و حواء،
and the remarkable shift in the boundaries
و التغير المهم في الحدود
between public and private which has occurred
بين ما هو عام و ما هو خاص الحادث
in the past 10 years.
في السنوات ال10 الماضية.
You know the incident.
أنت تعلم الحادثة.
Adam and Eve one day in the Garden of Eden
في يوم من الأيام في جنة عدن قد لاحظ آدم و حواء
realize they are naked.
أنهم عراة.
They freak out.
لقد فزعوا.
And the rest is history.
و حصل ما حصل.
Nowadays, Adam and Eve
لو عاش آدم و حواء في عصرنا هذا
would probably act differently.
لتصرفوا بشكل مختلف على الأرجح.
[@Adam Last nite was a blast! loved dat apple LOL]
[الليلة الماضية كانت رائعة! لقد أحببت هذه التفاحة هاهاها Adam@]
[@Eve yep.. babe, know what happened to my pants tho?]
[أجل عزيزي، لكن هل تعلم ماذا حصل لبنطالي؟ Eve@]
We do reveal so much more information
نحن نكشف العديد من المعلومات
about ourselves online than ever before,
عن أنفسنا على الإنترنت أكثر من أي وقت مضى،
and so much information about us
و الكثير من المعلومات عنا
is being collected by organizations.
تُجمع عن طريق المؤسسات.
Now there is much to gain and benefit
الآن، هناك فائدة كبيرة
from this massive analysis of personal information,
من التحليل العملاق للبيانات الشخصية،
or big data,
أو المعلومات الكثيرة،
but there are also complex tradeoffs that come
لكن هناك أيضاً مقايضات معقدة تنتج عن
from giving away our privacy.
تنازلنا عن خصوصيتنا.
And my story is about these tradeoffs.
و قصتي هي عن ثلاثة مقايضات.
We start with an observation which, in my mind,
دعنا نبدأ بملاحظة و التي، في رأيي،
has become clearer and clearer in the past few years,
تزداد وضوحاً منذ سنوات قليلة،
that any personal information
و هي أن أي معلومة شخصية
can become sensitive information.
يمكن أن تصبح معلومة حساسة.
Back in the year 2000, about 100 billion photos
في سنة 2000، تم التقاط حوالي
were shot worldwide,
100 بليون صورة حول العالم،
but only a minuscule proportion of them
لكن جزء صغير منها فقط
were actually uploaded online.
تم تحميله على الإنترنت.
In 2010, only on Facebook, in a single month,
في عام 2010، على موقع فيسبوك وحده، في شهر واحد،
2.5 billion photos were uploaded,
تم تحميل 2.5 بليون صورة،
most of them identified.
معظمها متعرف عليها.
In the same span of time,
في نفس الفترة الزمنية،
computers' ability to recognize people in photos
قد زادت قدرة الحواسيب على تعرف على الناس
improved by three orders of magnitude.
في الصور إلى ثلاثة أضعاف.
What happens when you combine
الأمر الذي يحدث عندما تدمج
these technologies together:
هاتين التقنيتين معاً:
increasing availability of facial data;
هو زيادة في توفر البيانات عن الوجوه؛
improving facial recognizing ability by computers;
مما يزيد من قدرة الحواسيب على التعرف على الوجوه؛
but also cloud computing,
لكن أيضاً اتصال الحواسيب الآني،
which gives anyone in this theater
الذي يوفر لجميع الموجودين في هذا المسرح
the kind of computational power
نفس القدرة الحاسوبية
which a few years ago was only the domain
التي كانت منذ سنوات قليلة
of three-letter agencies;
حكراً على المنظمات الأمنية؛
and ubiquitous computing,
و وجود قدرة الحاسوبية في كل الأجهزة،
which allows my phone, which is not a supercomputer,
مما يسمح لهاتفي، و هو ليس حاسوب فائق،
to connect to the Internet
بالاتصال بالانترنت
and do there hundreds of thousands
و عمل تطابق للمئات من الآلاف
of face metrics in a few seconds?
من صور الوجوه في ثواني قليلة.
Well, we conjecture that the result
حسناً، يخبرنا حدسنا أن نتيجة
of this combination of technologies
دمج هذه التقنيات
will be a radical change in our very notions
سوف يحدث تغير جذري في مفاهيمنا الخاصة
of privacy and anonymity.
للخصوصية و إخفاء الهوية.
To test that, we did an experiment
لاختبار ذلك، قمنا بعمل تجربة
on Carnegie Mellon University campus.
في حرم جامعة كارينجي ميلون.
We asked students who were walking by
طلبنا من الطلاب الذين كانوا يسيرون في المكان
to participate in a study,
أن يشاركوا في الدراسة،
and we took a shot with a webcam,
و أخذنا صورة لهم باستخدام كاميرا كمبيوتر،
and we asked them to fill out a survey on a laptop.
و طلبنا منهم أن يعبئوا استبيان على اللابتوب.
While they were filling out the survey,
و بينما كانوا يعبئون الاستبيان،
we uploaded their shot to a cloud-computing cluster,
قمنا بتحميل صورهم على شبكة من الحواسيب المتصلة،
and we started using a facial recognizer
و بدأنا باستخدام محلل صور
to match that shot to a database
لإيجاد تطابق للصورة على قاعدة بيانات
of some hundreds of thousands of images
تحتوي على المئات من الآلاف من الصور
which we had downloaded from Facebook profiles.
قمنا بتنزيلها من صفحات الفيسبوك الشخصية،
By the time the subject reached the last page
في الوقت الذي وصل فيه المشارك إلى آخر صفحة
on the survey, the page had been dynamically updated
في الاستبيان، تم تحديث الصفحة
with the 10 best matching photos
بأقرب 10 صور للمشارك
which the recognizer had found,
قد وجدها المتعرف،
and we asked the subjects to indicate
و طلبنا من المشاركين إخبارنا
whether he or she found themselves in the photo.
إن وجدوا أنفسهم في الصور.
Do you see the subject?
هل تستطيع رؤية المشارك؟
Well, the computer did, and in fact did so
حسناً، استطاع الحاسوب فعل ذلك، بالحقيقة استطاع
for one out of three subjects.
التعرف على واحد من كل ثلاثة مشاركين.
So essentially, we can start from an anonymous face,
إذاً الفكرة الرئيسية، هي أننا نستطيع أن نبدأ بوجه شخص غير معروف الهوية
offline or online, and we can use facial recognition
سواء موجود على أرض الواقع أو على الانترنت، ثم باستخدام خاصية التعرف على الوجوه
to give a name to that anonymous face
نستطيع معرفة اسم صاحب هذا الوجه
thanks to social media data.
بفضل بيانات شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي.
But a few years back, we did something else.
لكن، منذ بضع سنوات، كنا نقوم بأمر آخر.
We started from social media data,
كنا نبدأ ببيانات شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي،
we combined it statistically with data
و ندمجها إحصائياً ببيانات
from U.S. government social security,
من الأمن القومي الأمريكي،
and we ended up predicting social security numbers,
و استطعنا توقع أرقام الضمان الاجتماعي،
which in the United States
و التي تعد في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
are extremely sensitive information.
معلومات حساسة للغاية.
Do you see where I'm going with this?
هل ترون ما الذي أرمي إليه بهذا؟
So if you combine the two studies together,
إذاً إن دمجت الدراستين سوياً،
then the question becomes,
يصبح السؤال،
can you start from a face and,
هل يمكنك البدء بوجه شخص،
using facial recognition, find a name
و باستخدام خاصية التعرف على الوجوه، إيجاد اسم
and publicly available information
و معلومات متوفرة للعموم
about that name and that person,
عن هذا الاسم و هذا الشخص،
and from that publicly available information
و استخلاص من هذه المعلومات العامة
infer non-publicly available information,
معلومات خاصة،
much more sensitive ones
أكثر حساسية بكثير
which you link back to the face?
يمكنك ربطها بالوجه؟
And the answer is, yes, we can, and we did.
و الإجابة هي، نعم، تستطيع، و استطعنا نحن فعل ذلك.
Of course, the accuracy keeps getting worse.
بالطبع، إن الدقة تزداد سوءاً.
[27% of subjects' first 5 SSN digits identified (with 4 attempts)]
[تم معرفة أول خمسة أرقام من رقم الضمان الاجتماعي ل27% من المشاركين بالدراسة (بعد أربعة محاولات)]
But in fact, we even decided to develop an iPhone app
لكن في الحقيقة، لقد قررنا حتى تطوير تطبيق للآيفون
which uses the phone's internal camera
الذي يستخدم الكاميرا الداخلية للهاتف
to take a shot of a subject
لأخذ صورة الشخص
and then upload it to a cloud
ثم تحميلها على قاعدة بيانات على الانترنت
and then do what I just described to you in real time:
ثم يتم عمل ما قد وصفته لكم للتو آنياً:
looking for a match, finding public information,
البحث عن صورة مطابقة، إيجاد معلومات عامة،
trying to infer sensitive information,
محاولة استنتاج معلومات حساسة،
and then sending back to the phone
ثم إعادة إرسالها إلى الهاتف
so that it is overlaid on the face of the subject,
بحيث تضاف إلى صورة وجه المشارك،
an example of augmented reality,
إنه مثال للحقيقة المدمجة مع التكنولوجيا،
probably a creepy example of augmented reality.
على الأغلب هو مثال مريب للحقيقة المدمجة.
In fact, we didn't develop the app to make it available,
في الواقع، نحن لم نطور التطبيق لجعله متوفراً،
just as a proof of concept.
فقط لإثبات المبدأ.
In fact, take these technologies
في الواقع، خذ هذه التقنيات
and push them to their logical extreme.
و ادفع بها إلى أقصى حدود المنطق.
Imagine a future in which strangers around you
تخيل مستقبلاً حيث ينظر إليك الغرباء من حولك
will look at you through their Google Glasses
من خلال نظارات جوجل الخاصة بهم
or, one day, their contact lenses,
أو، في يوم ما، عدساتهم اللاصقة،
and use seven or eight data points about you
و يستخدموا سبعة أو ثمانية معلومات عنك
to infer anything else
لاستنتاج أي معلومة أخرى
which may be known about you.
يمكن أن تكون معروفة عنك.
What will this future without secrets look like?
كيف سوف يبدو هذا المستقبل الخالي من الأسرار؟
And should we care?
و هل علينا إبداء الاهتمام؟
We may like to believe
قد نود تصديق
that the future with so much wealth of data
أن المستقبل المليء بكم هائل من البيانات
would be a future with no more biases,
سوف يكون مستقبل بلا تحيز،
but in fact, having so much information
لكن في الحقيقة، امتلاك كم هائل من المعلومات
doesn't mean that we will make decisions
لا يعني أننا سوف نتخذ قرارات
which are more objective.
أكثر موضوعية.
In another experiment, we presented to our subjects
في تجربة أخرى، قدمنا للمشاركين لدينا
information about a potential job candidate.
معلومات عن متقدم محتمل لوظيفة.
We included in this information some references
لقد قمنا بإرفاق هذه المعلومة ببعض المصادر
to some funny, absolutely legal,
لبعض المعلومات المضحكة، و القانونية تماماً،
but perhaps slightly embarrassing information
لكن قد تكون محرجة قليلاً
that the subject had posted online.
قد أدخلها المشارك على شبكة الإنترنت.
Now interestingly, among our subjects,
الآن بشكل مفاجئ، من بين المشاركين،
some had posted comparable information,
بعضهم قد أدخل معلومات قابلة للمقارنة،
and some had not.
و البعض الآخر لم يفعل.
Which group do you think
أي المجموعتين تعتقدوا
was more likely to judge harshly our subject?
أنها كانت أقسى في تقييم مشاركنا؟
Paradoxically, it was the group
بشكل متناقض، لقد كانت المجموعة
who had posted similar information,
التي أدخلت معلومات مماثلة،
an example of moral dissonance.
إنه مثال على عدم الانسجام الأخلاقي.
Now you may be thinking,
الآن إنك قد تفكر،
this does not apply to me,
إن هذا لا ينطبق علي،
because I have nothing to hide.
لأن ليس لدي ما أخفيه.
But in fact, privacy is not about
لكن في الحقيقة، إن الخصوصية ليست متعلقة
having something negative to hide.
بإخفاء الأمور السلبية.
Imagine that you are the H.R. director
تخيل أنك مدير لقسم الموارد البشرية
of a certain organization, and you receive résumés,
في منظمة معينة، و وصلتك سيَر ذاتية،
and you decide to find more information about the candidates.
و قررت أن تجد معلومات أكثر عن المتقدمين.
Therefore, you Google their names
لهذا، فإنك تقوم بالبحث عن أسمائهم في جوجل
and in a certain universe,
و في وجود معين،
you find this information.
وجدت هذه المعلومة.
Or in a parallel universe, you find this information.
أو في وجود آخر، وجدت هذه المعلومة.
Do you think that you would be equally likely
هل تعتقد أنه سوف تكون احتمالات اتصالك
to call either candidate for an interview?
بأي منهما متساوية لإجراء مقابلة؟
If you think so, then you are not
إن كنت تعتقد كذلك، إذاً أنت لست
like the U.S. employers who are, in fact,
كأصحاب العمل الأمريكيين الذين، في الواقع،
part of our experiment, meaning we did exactly that.
جزء من تجربتنا، أي أننا قمنا باختبار ذلك تماماً.
We created Facebook profiles, manipulating traits,
قمنا بإنشاء صفحات شخصية على الفيسبوك، متلاعبين بالصفات،
then we started sending out résumés to companies in the U.S.,
ثم بدأنا بإرسال سير شخصية لشركات في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
and we detected, we monitored,
و قمنا بالكشف، و بمتابعة،
whether they were searching for our candidates,
إن كانوا يبحثون عن مرشحينا،
and whether they were acting on the information
و إن كانوا يتصرفون حيال المعلومات
they found on social media. And they were.
التي وجدوها على شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي. و بالفعل قاموا بذلك.
Discrimination was happening through social media
التفرقة بين المتقدمين ذي الكفاءة المتماثلة كانت حاصلة
for equally skilled candidates.
بناء على شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي.
Now marketers like us to believe
الآن يفضل المسوّقين أن نعتقد
that all information about us will always
أن كل المعلومات المتعلقة بنا سوف تستخدم دائماً
be used in a manner which is in our favor.
فيما يصب في مصلحتنا.
But think again. Why should that be always the case?
لكن فكر مرة أخرى. لماذا يجب ذلك أن يكون صحيحاً في كل مرة؟
In a movie which came out a few years ago,
في فيلم قد عرض منذ بضع سنوات،
"Minority Report," a famous scene
&amp;quot;تقرير الأقلية&amp;quot;، في لقطة مشهورة
had Tom Cruise walk in a mall
يسير توم كروز في مجمع تجاري
and holographic personalized advertising
و يظهر حوله إعلان ثلاثي الأبعاد من حوله تم تخصيصه
would appear around him.
تم تخصيصه ليتناسب مع شخصه.
Now, that movie is set in 2054,
الآن، تدور أحداث هذا الفيلم في عام 2054،
about 40 years from now,
حوالي 40 سنة من الآن.
and as exciting as that technology looks,
بقدر ما تبدو هذه التقنية مثيرة للاهتمام،
it already vastly underestimates
إلّا أن قدرها يستهان به بشكل كبير
the amount of information that organizations
كمية المعلومات التي تستطيع
can gather about you, and how they can use it
المنظمات جمعها عنك، و الكيفية التي تستخدمها بها
to influence you in a way that you will not even detect.
للتأثير بك بطريقة لن يمكنك حتى كشفها.
So as an example, this is another experiment
فكمثال، هذه تجربة أخرى
actually we are running, not yet completed.
لا تزال قيد الدراسة، لم تكتمل بعد.
Imagine that an organization has access
تخيل أن لمنظمة القدرة على الولوج
to your list of Facebook friends,
إلى قائمة أصدقاؤك على الفيسبوك،
and through some kind of algorithm
و من خلال خوارزمية معينة
they can detect the two friends that you like the most.
يستطيعون معرفة الصديقين المفضلين لديك.
And then they create, in real time,
و من ثم ينشئون، آنياً،
a facial composite of these two friends.
تركيب للوجه لهذين الصديقين.
Now studies prior to ours have shown that people
الآن أظهرت الدراسات السابقة لدراستنا أن الناس
don't recognize any longer even themselves
لا تستطيع التعرف حتى على أنفسها في
in facial composites, but they react
في رسومات تركيب الوجه، لكنهم يستجيبون
to those composites in a positive manner.
لهذه التراكيب بطريقة إيجابية.
So next time you are looking for a certain product,
لذا في المرة التالية التي تبحث فيها عن منتج معين،
and there is an ad suggesting you to buy it,
و هناك إعلان يقترح أن تشتريه،
it will not be just a standard spokesperson.
فإنه لن يتضمن متحدث عادي.
It will be one of your friends,
بل سيكون أحد أصدقاؤك،
and you will not even know that this is happening.
و لن تدرك حتى مالذي يحدث.
Now the problem is that
الآن المشكلة في ذلك
the current policy mechanisms we have
أن آليات السياسة التي نمتلكها
to protect ourselves from the abuses of personal information
لحماية أنفسنا من سوء استخدام المعلومات الشخصية
are like bringing a knife to a gunfight.
هي كإحضار سكين إلى قتال بالأسلحة النارية.
One of these mechanisms is transparency,
أحد هذه الآليات هي الشفافية،
telling people what you are going to do with their data.
إخبار الناس بما سوف تفعله ببياناتهم.
And in principle, that's a very good thing.
و كمبدأ، فإنه أمر جيد جداً.
It's necessary, but it is not sufficient.
إنه ضروري، لكنه ليس كافي.
Transparency can be misdirected.
يمكن للشفافية أن يتم توجيهها بصورة خاطئة.
You can tell people what you are going to do,
يمكنك إخبار الناس بما سوف تقوم به،
and then you still nudge them to disclose
ثم لاتزال تدفعهم إلى الإدلاء
arbitrary amounts of personal information.
بكميات كبيرة من المعلومات الشخصية.
So in yet another experiment, this one with students,
لذا في تجربة أخرى، هذه المرة مع طلاب،
we asked them to provide information
فقد طلبنا منهم توفير معلومات
about their campus behavior,
عن تصرفاتهم داخل الحرم الجامعي،
including pretty sensitive questions, such as this one.
تتضمن أسئلة حساسة للغاية، كهذا.
[Have you ever cheated in an exam?]
[هل غششت مرة في إمتحان؟]
Now to one group of subjects, we told them,
الآن أحد المجموعات من المشاركين، قلنا لهم،
"Only other students will see your answers."
&amp;quot;فقط الطلاب الآخرون سوف يروا إجاباتكم.&amp;quot;
To another group of subjects, we told them,
لمجموعة أخرى من المشاركين، قلنا لهم،
"Students and faculty will see your answers."
&amp;quot;إن الطلاب و أعضاء الهيئة التدريسية سوف يروا إجاباتكم.&amp;quot;
Transparency. Notification. And sure enough, this worked,
شفافية. إخطار. و بالطبع، نجح الأمر،
in the sense that the first group of subjects
من ناحية أن المجموعة الأولى من المشاركين
were much more likely to disclose than the second.
كانت أكثر قابلية للإدلاء من المجموعة الثانية.
It makes sense, right?
إنه أمر منطقي، أليس كذلك؟
But then we added the misdirection.
لكننا أضفنا سوء التوجيه بعد ذلك.
We repeated the experiment with the same two groups,
لقد كررنا التجربة مع نفس المجموعتين،
this time adding a delay
لكن بإضافة تأخير هذه المرة
between the time we told subjects
بين زمن إخبار المشتركين
how we would use their data
بالكيفية التي سيتم استخدام بياناتهم بها
and the time we actually started answering the questions.
و زمن الإجابة على الأسئلة.
How long a delay do you think we had to add
كم طول التأخير الذي تتوقعون كان علينا إضافته
in order to nullify the inhibitory effect
لإزالة التأثير الممانع
of knowing that faculty would see your answers?
لمعرفة أن أحد أعضاء هيئة التدريس سوف يرى إجابتك؟
Ten minutes?
عشرة دقائق؟
Five minutes?
خمسة دقائق؟
One minute?
دقيقة؟
How about 15 seconds?
ماذا عن 15 ثانية؟
Fifteen seconds were sufficient to have the two groups
كانت 15 ثانية كافية لجعل المجموعتين تدليان
disclose the same amount of information,
تدليان بنفس الكمية من المعلومات،
as if the second group now no longer cares
و كأن المجموعة الثانية لم تعد تهتم الآن
for faculty reading their answers.
بأمر قراءة أعضاء هيئة الدريس لأجوبتهم.
Now I have to admit that this talk so far
الآن عليّ الاعتراف أن هذا الحديث حتى الآن
may sound exceedingly gloomy,
قد يبدو كئيب لدرجة كبيرة،
but that is not my point.
لكن هذا ليس هدفي.
In fact, I want to share with you the fact that
بالواقع، أود أن أشارككم حقيقة أنه
there are alternatives.
هناك بدائل.
The way we are doing things now is not the only way
إن الطريقة التي نستخدمها في إنجاز الأمور الآن هي ليست الطريقة الوحيدة
they can done, and certainly not the best way
لإنجازها، و مؤكداً هي ليست أفضل طريقة
they can be done.
لإنجازها.
When someone tells you, "People don't care about privacy,"
عندما يخبرك شخص ما: &amp;quot;إن الناس لا تهتم بالخصوصية،&amp;quot;
consider whether the game has been designed
فكر إن كان تم تصميم اللعبة
and rigged so that they cannot care about privacy,
و تزويرها كي لا يستطيعوا الاهتمام بالخصوصية،
and coming to the realization that these manipulations occur
و إدراك أن هذه التلاعبات حاصلة
is already halfway through the process
هو نصف الطريق في عملية
of being able to protect yourself.
حماية نفسك.
When someone tells you that privacy is incompatible
عندما يخبرك شخص أن الخصوصية لا تتوافق
with the benefits of big data,
مع فوائد البيانات الهائلة،
consider that in the last 20 years,
فكر أن في ال20 سنة الماضية،
researchers have created technologies
طور الباحثون تقنيات
to allow virtually any electronic transactions
للسماح عملياً لأي عملية إلكترونية
to take place in a more privacy-preserving manner.
أن تحصل بطريقة أكثر حفظاً للسرية.
We can browse the Internet anonymously.
نحن نستطيع تصفح الانترنت بسرية.
We can send emails that can only be read
نستطيع إرسال رسائل إلكترونية يمكن قراءتها فقط
by the intended recipient, not even the NSA.
بواسطة الشخص المستقبل، و لا حتى الإن أس أيه (وكالة الأمن القومي) يمكنها ذلك.
We can have even privacy-preserving data mining.
يمكننا حتى استخراج البيانات بطريقة تحفظ السرية.
In other words, we can have the benefits of big data
بمعنى آخر، نحن بإمكاننا التمتع بفوائد البيانات الهائلة
while protecting privacy.
مع حماية السرية.
Of course, these technologies imply a shifting
بالطبع، هذه التقنيات تعني تغير
of cost and revenues
في التكاليف و الإيرادات
between data holders and data subjects,
بين حافظين البيانات و أصحاب البيانات،
which is why, perhaps, you don't hear more about them.
يمكن، لهذا السبب، أنت لا تسمع المزيد عنها.
Which brings me back to the Garden of Eden.
الأمر الذي يعيدني إلى جنة عدن.
There is a second privacy interpretation
هناك تفسير آخر متعلق بالخصوصية
of the story of the Garden of Eden
في قصة جنة عدن
which doesn't have to do with the issue
و هو ليس له علاقة بقضية
of Adam and Eve feeling naked
شعور آدم و حواء بالعري
and feeling ashamed.
و بالحرج.
You can find echoes of this interpretation
تستطيع إيجاد لمحات عن هذا التفسير
in John Milton's "Paradise Lost."
في قصيدة جون ملتون &amp;quot;الفردوس المفقود&amp;quot;.
In the garden, Adam and Eve are materially content.
في الجنة، إن آدم و حواء مكتفيين مادياً.
They're happy. They are satisfied.
إنهما سعداء. إنهما مكتفيين.
However, they also lack knowledge
على الرغم من ذلك، فإنهم أيضاً يفتقرون المعرفة
and self-awareness.
و إدراك الذات.
The moment they eat the aptly named
و في لحظة إلتقامهما الفاكهة المسماة
fruit of knowledge,
بفاكهة المعرفة،
that's when they discover themselves.
هنا قد اكتشفا نفسيهما.
They become aware. They achieve autonomy.
لقد أصبحا مدركين. لقد حصلا على الاستقلالية الذاتية.
The price to pay, however, is leaving the garden.
لكن، الثمن الذي يجب دفعة، هو ترك الجنة.
So privacy, in a way, is both the means
إذا فالخصوصية، بطريقة ما، هي الوسيلة
and the price to pay for freedom.
و الثمن الذي يجب دفعه مقابل الحرية.
Again, marketers tell us
مجدداً، يخبرنا المسوّقون
that big data and social media
أن البيانات الهائلة و شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي
are not just a paradise of profit for them,
هي ليست فقط مصدر كبير للربح بالنسبة لهم،
but a Garden of Eden for the rest of us.
لكنها جنة عدن بالنسبة لبقيتنا.
We get free content.
نحن نحصل على محتويات مجانية.
We get to play Angry Birds. We get targeted apps.
نستطيع لعب &amp;quot;أنجري بيردز&amp;quot;. نستطيع الحصول على تطبيقات موجهة.
But in fact, in a few years, organizations
لكن في الحقيقة، بعد عدة سنوات، سوف
will know so much about us,
تعلم المنظمات الكثير عنا،
they will be able to infer our desires
سوف يستطيعوا استنتاج رغباتنا
before we even form them, and perhaps
قبل حتى تكويننا لها، و ربما
buy products on our behalf
قد يشتروا منتجات باسمنا
before we even know we need them.
حتى قبل معرفتنا أننا نحتاجها.
Now there was one English author
الأن لقد كان هناك مؤلف بريطاني
who anticipated this kind of future
قد توقع هذا النوع من المستقبل
where we would trade away
حيث سوف نتخلى عن
our autonomy and freedom for comfort.
استقلالنا الذاتي و حريتنا من أجل الراحة.
Even more so than George Orwell,
حتى أكثر من جورج أرويل،
the author is, of course, Aldous Huxley.
إن المؤلف هو، بالطبع، ألدوس هكسلي.
In "Brave New World," he imagines a society
في كتابه &amp;quot;العالم الجديد الشجاع،&amp;quot; إنه يتصور مجتمع
where technologies that we created
حيث تصبح التكنولوجيا التي طورناها
originally for freedom
أساساً من أجل الحرية
end up coercing us.
مصدر إجبار لنا.
However, in the book, he also offers us a way out
لكن، في الكتاب، هو يوفر لنا مخرج
of that society, similar to the path
من ذلك المجتمع، كالذي
that Adam and Eve had to follow to leave the garden.
اضطر آدم و حواء اتخاذه للخروج من الجنة.
In the words of the Savage,
بكلمات مقتبسة من فلم &amp;quot;الوحش&amp;quot;،
regaining autonomy and freedom is possible,
&amp;quot;إن استرجاع الاستقلالية الذاتية و الحرية ممكن،
although the price to pay is steep.
على الرغم من أن الثمن باهظ.&amp;quot;
So I do believe that one of the defining fights
فإذاً إنني أؤمن أن أحد النضالات الحاسمة
of our times will be the fight
في زمننا سوف يكون النضال
for the control over personal information,
من أجل التحكم بالمعلومات الشخصية،
the fight over whether big data will become a force
النضال حول إذا ما كانت البيانات الهائلة سوف تصبح قوة
for freedom,
دافعة للحرية،
rather than a force which will hiddenly manipulate us.
بدلاً من أن تكون قوة تتلاعب بنا بالخفاء.
Right now, many of us
الآن، الكثير منا
do not even know that the fight is going on,
لا يعلم أن القتال جاري،
but it is, whether you like it or not.
لكنه كذلك، سواء شئت أم أبيت.
And at the risk of playing the serpent,
و مع مجازفة اللعب مع الأفعى،
I will tell you that the tools for the fight
سوف أخبركم أن الأدوات للقتال
are here, the awareness of what is going on,
موجودة، إن إدراك الحاصل،
and in your hands,
في يديك،
just a few clicks away.
فقط على بعد نقرات.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)